晚上好 West先生
Good evening, Mr. West.
三等车厢 到伦敦桥
Third-class London Bridge.
单程还是往返?
Single or return?
噢 无所谓啦 单程
Oh, it doesn't matter, single.
快点
Quickly,
快一点
quickly.
他死了
He's dead,
一定是从火车上掉下来了
must have fallen from the train.
是啊 看他的头
Yeah, look at his head.
你回去警局
You run back to the station
报告这里的情况
and tell'em what happened,
我守在这里
I'll stay here.
好一场浓雾啊
It's a real pea souper
报纸上有什么趣闻吗 华生?
Nothing in the paper, Watson?
没有
No.
南非又一场革命爆发
There's another revolution in South America,
也许非洲要开战了
possible war in Africa,
没有你感兴趣的
nothing of interest to you.
伦敦的罪犯们真是没用
The London Criminal is certainly a dull fellow.
这样的天气里 盗贼和杀人犯 可以在伦敦街头闲庭信步
A thief or a murderer could roam London on a day like this
就像丛林里的老虎
as the tiger does the jungle,
当发起突袭的那一刻
unseen until he pounces,
受害者才会发觉
and then evident only to his victim.
有很多小毛贼啊
There are numerous petty thefts.
那种阴森的大舞台
Well, this great and somber stage
是为更带劲的情况准备的
is set for something more worthy than that.
我不是罪犯
It is fortunate for the community
真是国家的大幸啊
that I am not a criminal.
那倒没错
It is indeed.
那些暗杀横行拉丁国家 没有这样的浓雾天
It is well they don't have days of fog in the Latin countries,
真是走运
the countries of assassination.
给你的 福尔摩斯先生
For you, Mr. Holmes.
谢谢
Thank you.
-福尔摩斯先生... -我知道
-Mr. Holmes... -Yes, I know.
-你的... -对于房间的事情我很抱歉
-Your... -I apologize for the state of my room.
什么事
Well, well, what next?
我哥哥Mycroft要来了
My brother Mycroft is coming around.
噢 有什么奇怪的
Oh, why not.
有什么奇怪的
Why not?
就像见到一辆电车
As if you met a tram-car
行驶在乡间小路
coming down a country lane.
Mycroft有他自己的轨道
Mycroft has his lines and he runs on them.
他出入繁华地段的住所
Now, his Pall Mall Lodgings,
穿梭于Diogenes俱乐部 白厅...
the Diogenes Club, Whitehall...
那是他的圈子
that's his cycle.
他只来过这里一次
Once and only once has he ever been here.
我是说 什么样的事会惊动他呢
I mean what upheaval can possibly have derailed him?
"为Cadogan West一事 必须见你"
Must see you over Cadogan West.
"即刻到"
Coming at once.
"Mycroft"
Mycroft.
我听过这个名字
I've heard the name.
我可什么都没想起来
That recalls nothing to my mind.
Mycroft打破他古怪的作风
Mycroft breaking out of this erratic fashion,
太反常了
It's extraordinary.
华生 你知道Mycroft是干什么的吧
Watson, you do know what Mycroft is.
我只记得那一次
I seem to remember about the time,
那个希腊翻译员的案子
of the affair of the Greek interpreter.
你告诉我 他在英国政府里的
You told me that he had some small office
某个小办公室就职
under the British government.
那阵子他不太顺
He wasn't doing quite so well in those days.
他的位置是独一无二的
His position is unique.
他自己取得的
He's made it for himself.
前无古人
There's never been anything like it before
后无来者
nor will be again.
他的头脑清晰 条理缜密
He is the tidiest and most orderly brain
记忆力惊人
with the greatest capacity for storing facts
无人能及
of any man living.
政府的每一个结论
The conclusions of every government department
都要经他的手
that passed through him.
他是中心交换站
He is the central exchange
一切都由他来平衡
which makes out the balance.
其它人是专家
All other men are specialists.
而他的专长是无所不知
His specialism is omniscience.
一次又一次
Time and time again
Mycroft的一句话决定了国家的政策
Mycroft's word has decided national policy.
多么神奇的人物啊
Then Jupiter himself.
而他今天居然会来拜访我们
Is descending upon us today.
是啊
Yes, indeed.
-还是不知道Cadogan West是谁 -West...
-No trace of Cadogan West. -West...
我这里有
I have it, yes.
Cadogan West
Cadogan West,
Cadogan West 是个青年
Cadogan West was the young man
周二被发现
who was found dead on the underground
死在地铁里
on Tuesday morning.
噢 是啊 是啊
Oh, yes, yes, yes, yes.
这种平淡无奇的案子
It was a featureless case as I remember,
年轻人从火车上掉下来
young man killed falling from a moving train,
没有抢夺和暴力的痕迹
no robbery, no violence.
华生  Mycroft来了
Watson, Brother Mycroft.
还有我们一个老朋友
That looks like our old friend
Bradstreet警官
Inspector Bradstreet.
他干吗要带个警察来?
Why should he bring a policeman with him?
啊 找到了
Ah, here we are.
Cadogan West
Cadogan West,
Woolwich军工厂职员 27岁 未婚
Clerk at the Woolwich Arsenal, 27, unmarried.
政府雇员
Government employee.
和我哥哥有关系啦
Behold a link with my brother Mycroft.
Mycroft
Mycroft.
啊 这位是...
Ah, Dr...
华生
Watson.
华生...你们认识Bradstreet
Watson.You know Bradstreet.
福尔摩斯  华生医生
Holmes, Dr. Watson.
Cadogan West
Cadogan West,
最棘手的问题 夏洛克
the most annoying business, Sherlock.
我非常不喜欢改变我的习惯
I extremely dislike altering my habits
可当局让我无可辩驳
with the powers that be would broke no denial.
目前暹罗的情况之下
In the present state of Siam
我离开办公室真是雪上加霜
it's most awkward I should be away from the office
但这是真正的危机 夏洛克
but it is a real crisis Sherlock.
我从没见过首相这样不安
I've never seen the Prime Minister so upset
整个海军部
and as to the Admiralty,
好像个炸了的蜜蜂窝
buzzing like an overturned beehive.
请坐吧 Bradstreet
Do sit down Bradstreet.
这些报纸上
Well, there's nothing unusual
没写什么特别的
reported in the newspapers.
我希望没写
I should hope not.
那个可怜的年轻人
The wretched youth,
他衣服口袋里 装着布鲁斯-帕廷顿潜水艇计划
had the plans of the Bruce Partington submarine in his pocket.
你们一定听说过
Well, you must have heard of it.
只听过名字
Only by name.
它的重要性怎么说都不过分
Its importance can hardly be exaggerated.
这是政府
It has been the most closely guarded
最严格保密的秘密
of all government secrets.
我可以告诉你们
You may take it from me that navel warfare
在布鲁斯-帕廷顿的效力范围以内
becomes impossible within the radius
海战就不会发生
of a Bruce Partington operation.
那么 我们在讨论的
So, what sort of plans
是计划的哪一部分?
are we talking about?
最难以理解的部分 夏洛克
Extremely intricate ones, Sherlock.
30页纸
Some 30 different pages,
每一页对整体都至关重要
each one essential to the working of the whole.
这些计划通常放在哪里?
Where are the plans normally kept?
在一个紧挨着Woolwich军工厂的
In an elaborate safe
机密办公室
in a confidential office
放在精密保险箱里
adjoining the arsenal of Woolwich
办公室还装有防盗门窗
with burglar proof doors and windows.
即使是海军将军
If the chief instructor of the Navy himself
想参阅这些计划
desired to consult the plans,
他一定得到Woolwich去
he would have to go to Woolwich to do so.
从一个死去的小职员口袋里
To think they should turn up in the pocket
翻出伦敦最重要的东西
of a dead Junior Clerk
想一想就觉得可怕
in the heart of London is simply awful.
你们找回那些计划书了吗?
Have you recovered the papers?
没有 夏洛克 没有
No, Sherlock, no.
这就是棘手的地方
That's the pinch.
没有找到
We have not.
有10页计划书被从Woolwich拿走了
Some ten papers were taken from Woolwich.
可是只在Cadogan West的口袋里
Only seven were found
找到了7页
in the pocket of Cadogan West.
另外的3页
The other three are
没了 不见了
missing, gone, vanished, stolen.
你必须放下所有的事情 夏洛克
You must drop everything, Sherlock.
别管你那些治安法庭负责的小破案子了
Never mind your usual petty puzzles of the police courts.
这是真正的国际大案
This is a real international crisis
你一定得解决的大案
that you have to solve.
我想 这个案子
Well, there are some points of interest
确实有些地方很让我感兴趣
in the case I suppose.
我很乐意去调查
I'll be pleased to look into it.
啊
Ah.
Bradstreet 都有谁掌管保险柜的钥匙?
Bradstreet, now, who held the keys to that safe?
一共有两串钥匙
There are two sets of keys.
James Walter先生拿着一串
Sir James Walter holds one set.
他是管理秘密文件的官员
He is the actual official guardian of the papers.
一个鞠躬尽瘁的老官员
A man grown gray in the service of the State,
上流社会颇受人欢迎的客人
a favored guest in the most exalted houses.
他的爱国主义不容置疑 可以免除嫌疑
His patriotism is above suspicion.
另一串呢?
And the other keys?
Sidney Johnson先生
A Mr. Sidney Johnson,
高级职员 也是制图员
a Senior Clerk and Draughtsman.
一个沉默寡言的男人
A silent morose man,
不爱社交 但工作尽心尽力
not popular but a hard worker.
他有妻子作证
His wife corroborates
他是清白的
his account of the matter.
周一整个晚上他都在家里
He was at home the whole of Monday night
钥匙从没离开过表链
and the keys never left the watch-chain
一直好端端挂在那
upon which they hang.
那个叫West的是什么人?
What sort of fellow was this man West?
鲁莽的热血青年
Hot-headed, rather impetuous,
他的工作
his duties brought him
需要他每天和计划书打交道
into daily contact with the plans.
那天晚上是谁锁的保险柜?
Who locked them up that night?
Johnson 那个高级职员
Johnson, the Senior Clerk.
但是后来却出现在
But yet they were found on the person
一个初级职员的口袋里
of the Junior Clerk.
我是说结论不是很明显吗
Well, I mean that sounds final, does it not?
是啊 可是他为什么要拿走呢?
Yeah, but why would he take them?
他拿走计划 除了拿到伦敦去卖
Reason why he should take them
还能有别的原因吗?
up to London except to sell them.
没了
Nope.
那么这就是我们的破案前提
Then we must take that as our working hypothesis.
West 他有没有可能
West, could he have done this
制作了备用钥匙?
with false keys?
他打开保险柜 取走文件
He opens the safe, takes out the papers,
去伦敦见一个外国特务
goes off to London to see a foreign agent.
他必须在早上之前带回来
He has to have'em back before morning
否则就会被发现了
or the loss will be discovered.
他拿走了10页
He took away ten.
7页在口袋里
Seven were in his pocket.
剩下3页呢?
What became of the other three?
他本人当然不想
He certainly wouldn't leave
落下那3页文件
them of his own free will.
我都明白了
It all seems perfectly clear to me.
如你所说 福尔摩斯先生
As you say, Mr. Holmes,
West偷了计划书 打算卖掉
West stole the plans in order to sell them.
他去见了特务
He met the agent
但是价格上有了分歧
but they could not agree as to a price.
所以West转身回家
So West returned home again
而特务一直跟着他
but the agent followed him.
在火车上 干掉了他
In the train the agent murdered him,
带走了最精华的几页
took the more, essential papers,
并把尸体从火车上抛了下来
and threw the body from the railway carriage.
一切都解释得通了 对不对?
Now, that would explain everything, would it not?
很好
It's good,
非常好 Bradstreet
that's very good, Bradstreet.
你的理论很完整
Your theory holds together.
可如果这是真的 这个案子就了结了
But if this is true then the case is at an end.
一方面 叛国者已经伏法
On the one hand the traitor is dead,
另一方面
on the other
布鲁斯-帕廷顿潜水艇计划
the plans of the Bruce Partington submarine
现在大概已经到了某个大陆
are presumably somewhere on the continent.
我是说 我还能做什么呢?
I mean what is there for me to do?
行动吧 夏洛克
To act Sherlock,
行动
to act.
我的直觉不相信这种解释
All my instincts are against this explanation
我认为 你也一样
and yours too, I think.
手足之情不是空话
We are not brothers for nothing.
利用你的能力
Use your powers.
到现场去
Go to the scene.
提问相关的人员
Question the people concerned.
想方设法
Leave no stone unturned.
在你的侦探生涯中
In all of your career
再也找不到这样一个机会
you'll never have a greater chance
为你的国家效力呢
of serving your country.
如果你这边
If you on your part
可以给我一份完整的
will be kind enough to send me a complete list
已知在英国的
of foreign spies and international agents
国外间谍和国际特务的名单
known to be in England
和他们的地址
and their full address.
我们这边
And then we on our part
可以开始我们的调查了
can begin our investigation
先去一趟Longhead车站
by a visit to Longhead Station
Bradstreet
Bradstreet.
华生
Watson,
Hudson太太 我们要走了
Mrs. Hudson, we're leaving.
尸体是什么时间发现的?
When was the body found?
大概六点左右 先生
Near enough to six o'clock, sir,
周二早上
Tuesday morning.
他一定是周一晚上什么时间
He must have fallen from the train
从火车上掉下来的
some time Monday night.
车架上有没有发现
Have the carriages been examined
任何打斗的痕迹?
for any signs of violence?
没有争斗的痕迹
No such trace of violence had been found.
没有报告说车门是开着的?
No report of a door found open?
从他的车票上
We can tell the approximate time
我们可以估计出他上车的时间
that he entered the train from his ticket.
尸体上没发现车票
There was no ticket on the body.
那真是奇怪了
That is really very singular.
以我的经验
Then in my experience it's not possible
不出示车票
to reach the platform of the Metropolitan Line
是无法登上月台的 对不对?
without exhibiting one's ticket, is that not so?
是的 先生
Quite correct, sir.
不过 也许是凶手在把尸体抛出火车之前
Surely, the murderer would have removed the ticket
拿走了车票
before throwing West from the train
这样就无法发现
so as not to reveal the name of the station
离特务的住处最近的车站是哪里了
nearest his place of residents.
我想医生说得很对
I think the doctor has it.
他身上除了计划书和车票不见了之外
What else did he have in his possession
还发现了什么?
besides the fabled papers and no ticket?
只是些常用物品
Usual things,
笔记本 钱包 支票簿
pocketbook, notecase, checkbook.
噢 还有两张Woolwich剧院
Oh, and two tickets for the Dress Circle
前排座位的戏票
of the Woolwich Theater
时间是当晚
for that very evening.
看上去 West打算
It appears that West was to have attended
和他的未婚妻一起去看戏
the performance in the accompany of his fiance,
Violet Westbury小姐
Ms. Violet Westbury.
她是当晚最后一个见到他还活着的人
She was the last person to see him alive on that fatal night.
他们一起去剧院
They were walking to the theater together
走到公园的时候 他突然离开了她
in the park when he suddenly left her.
-没有解释就走了? -没有
-Suddenly without explanation. -NO.
铁轨上没有任何血迹?
There appears to be no bleeding on the line?
嗯 那里没有发现任何血迹
Well, there was hardly any trace of blood to be found.
据我推测
As I gather
一个人从开动的火车上掉下来
there was a considerable wound
一定会有相当大的伤口
consistent with a man falling from a moving train.
那是相当可怕
Well, it was a terrible thing to see.
据报告是脑部遭到重击
Said the head was knocked right in
头骨破裂而死
and the bone crushed.
没有特别的外部伤痕
And yet, there was no great external injury.
我想应该会有血迹
Well, I would expect some blood.
火车是往东北边开的
So the line runs northeast.
是的 铁轨从这里分开 先生
Yes, the track divides here sir,
这里一条支线向南
and there's a branch line goes south under the river
开往Rotherhive和New Cross
to Rotherhive and New Cross.
交叉点
The point.
The point
我想整个铁路系统上面
I suppose there are no great number
没有几个这样的交叉点吧?
of points in the system such as this?
很少 先生
There are very few, sir.
交叉点
Points,
弯曲
and a curve,
啊 如果真是这样的话
oh by Jove, If it were only so.
是什么
What is it?
福尔摩斯 你发现线索了?
Holmes, do you have a clue?
只是一个想法 Bradstreet
Well, it's an idea Bradstreet,
一个迹象而已
an indication no more.
不过这个案子突然有意思起来了
But the case certainly grows in interest
很奇特
It's unique,
非常奇特
Perfectly unique.
为什么不呢
And yet why not?
出租马车!
Cab!
这里有我们要的东西 华生
There is material here, Watson,
大有余地
there is scope.
我当初没发现这种可能 真是迟钝
I was dull indeed not to see it's possibilities.
我承认是挺迟钝
Well I confess it's dull to me.
我也是
And to me also,
但现在我有了一个想法
but I now have a hold of an idea
也许能带我们更进一步
which may lead us far.
现在轮到James先生了
Now I think, Sir James,
计划书的保管者
the guardian of the plans
是我们最先该注住的人
claims our first attention.
去Mumstead Hall
Mumstead Hall.
福尔摩斯?
Well, Holmes?
你的想法是?
Your idea?
噢 是的
Oh, yes.
那个West的死亡
The man West was killed
不是因为从车上掉下来
not by falling
也不是从火车上扔出来
or being thrown from a moving train.
他是在别的地方送命的
He met his death elsewhere
然后尸体被人放到了车顶上
and his body was on the roof of the carriage.
车顶上?
On the roof?
想想吧
Well, consider the facts.
发现尸体的地方
Is it a coincidence that the body was found
恰好在火车到达交叉点
in the very place
制动并转弯的地方
where the train brakes and sways
这难道是巧合吗?
as it comes round on the points?
突然的减速
The sudden slowing
不会影响车厢内的物体
would affect no object inside the carriage
但是车顶上的尸体则另当别论
but an object such as a body on the roof.
血迹也是问题
And there's the question of the blood.
当然了 如果尸体的血流在别处
Of course, there was no bleeding on the line
当然不会在铁轨上发现血迹了
if the body bled elsewhere.
每一个事实都佐证了这个说法
Each fact is suggestive in itself.
合起来就是一个结论
Together they have a cumulative force.
对了 还有车票
Yes, and the ticket too.
那也可以解释失踪的车票
That would explain the absence of the ticket.
华生 一切都符合了
Watson, it all fits together.
请等一下
Please wait.
先生们 请进
Come in please gentlemen.
我们在等你
We were expecting you.
啊 先生们
Ah, gentlemen.
Baines 谢谢
Thank you Baines.
谢谢 先生
Thank you, sir.
请跟我来 遗体在楼上
If you follow me the body is upstairs.
等 等一下
But wait, one moment.
你们不是承办葬礼的人吗?
Are you not the undertakers?
不好意思 James先生
Excuse me, Sir James.
呃 我是华生医生
Uh, I am Dr. Watson and, um,
这位是夏洛克 福尔摩斯先生
this is Mr. Sherlock Holmes.
我的主啊
Good heavens.
我们在帮助当局
We are helping the authorities
寻找失踪的文件
in the case of the missing papers.
我哥哥 James Walter爵士
My brother, Sir James Walter,
今天早晨去世了
died this morning.
我是Valentine Walter上校
I am Colonel Valentine Walter.
请这边来
Please gentlemen, come here.
我们非常遗憾 先生
We are very sorry, sir.
谢谢
Thank you.
我知道 这非常突然
I'm afraid it has been a great shock.
我可不可以问一下
May I ask
你哥哥是怎么去世的?
how did your brother die?
真是难以启齿
It was this horrible scandal.
我哥哥...
My brother is...
我哥哥是一个有着强烈荣誉感的人
my brother was a man of very sensitive honor.
他一直为自己主管的部门
He was fiercely proud
工作效率之高感到自豪
of the efficiency of his department.
计划书遭窃 对他是个致命的打击
The theft of the plans was a crushing blow.
他伤透了心
It broke his heart.
我们本希望James爵士
We were hoping Sir James
能帮助我们
might have been able to help.
我向你们保证
I assure you
他和我们一样
it was as much a mystery to him
对此大感不解
as it to all of us.
显然 他毫不怀疑West有罪
Naturally he had no doubt that West was guilty
但他为什么要这样做
but why he should have done such a thing.
现在 我们无从得知了
Now, of course, we shall never know.
那么 也许你可以指点一二?
So, you can turn a light on the matter?
我?
Me?
恐怕我除了道听途说之外
I'm afraid I know nothing
一无所知
say what I've read or heard.
-你从没见过Cadogan West? -没见过
-And you never meet Cadogan West? -No.
我很久没有回国了
No, I have not been back in the country long.
我哥哥为一个高度机密的机构工作
My brother's work was of a very highly-confidential nature.
他从不跟我透露
He did not discuss it with me.
先生们 我不想失礼
Gentlemen, I do not wish to discourteous
不过目前 我们非常狼狈
but we are much disturbed at present.
我冒昧恳请您结束这次谈话
I must ask you to hasten this interview to an end.
好的 很抱歉我们给您添麻烦了
Yes, we're sorry to have caused you so much trouble.
真是意想不到的发展
That's an unexpected development.
心力衰竭
Heart failure.
或是自杀
Or suicide.
该轮到Westbury小姐了
Now for Miss. Westbury.
死者的未婚妻?
Is that the dead man's fiancee?
没错
Yes.
我没法解释 福尔摩斯先生
I cannot explain it, Mr. Holmes.
自从悲剧发生我就没合过眼
I haven't closed my eyes since the tragedy
我不停地想啊想啊
thinking and thinking and thinking
事实会是什么样子
what the true meaning of it can be.
请坐
Do sit down.
Arthur是最诚实
Arthur was the most single-minded,
最有骑士风度 最爱国的人
chivalrous, patriotic man on earth.
他宁愿切掉自己的右手
He would have cut off his right-hand
也不会出卖
rather than sell a State secret
由他保管的国家机密
confided to his keeping.
对了解他的人来说 这是非常荒谬 绝对不可能的事情
It's absurd, impossible, preposterous to anyone who knew him.
事实上 Westbury小姐
The facts Ms. Westbury.
-他缺钱吗? -不
-Was he want of money? -No.
他的生活非常简单
His needs were very simple
他的薪水也很丰厚
and his salary was sufficient.
他已经攒了几百磅
He'd saved a few hundreds
我们打算新年的时候结婚
and we were to marry at the new year.
会不会受到什么精神上的刺激呢?
Was there any sign of mental excitement?
说吧 Westbury小姐
Come, Ms. Westbury,
对我们不妨直言
be absolutely frank with us.
我有一种感觉
I had a feeling
他是有些想法
there was something on his mind.
多久了?
How long?
大概是上周或者上上周开始
Only the last week or two.
有一次我问他
Once I asked him about it.
事情太严重 对你也不能说
It is too serious to speak about
他是这么回答的
even to you he said.
说下去 Westbury小姐
Go on, Ms. Westbury
即使也许会对他不利
even if it seems to turn against him.
我们也不知道接下来会怎样
We cannot say where it might lead us.
有天晚上他谈到...一个秘密
He spoke one evening about a,a secret.
我想他是说
I think he said that no doubt
外国间谍无疑会出大价钱
foreign spies would pay a great deal to have it.
他说我们管理松散
He said that we were slack about such matters
如果有叛徒监守自盗
and it would be easy for a traitor
那是非常容易的事情
to get hold of the plans.
噢 福尔摩斯先生
Oh, Mr. Holmes,
如果您可以
if you could only,
可以挽回他的名誉
only save his honor.
那对他意义重大
It was so much to him.
我会尽力的
I'll do what I can.
请跟我讲讲最后那个晚上
Now, please tell us about that last evening.
那是周一的晚上
It was Monday night
我们本来要去剧场
and we were to go to the theater.
Violet
Violet,
我恐怕要离开一下
I'm afraid I've got to leave you.
离开?
Leave me?
事情非常 非常重要
It's very, very important.
对不起
I'm sorry.
你最好回家去
You better go home.
马上回家吧
Go home immediately, please.
就是这里 福尔摩斯先生
It was just here, Mr. Holmes.
他一言不发就离开了?
And he disappeared without any explanation?
是的
Yes.
你确定当时就是在这里?
You are sure this is the exact spot?
是的
Yes.
我们约会的时候
We often used to meet here
经常在这里见面
when we were courting.
你可以看到
You see that's the building
他工作的地方
where he used to work.
噢
Oh.
那是我最后一次见到他
That was the last time I saw him.
华生 麻烦你
Watson will you be so kind
叫一辆马车 送Westbury小姐回家
as to take Miss Westbury home in a cab.
太糟糕了 非常糟糕
It's bad, it's really bad
没错 Jones先生
Of course, Mr. Jones.
这里整个乱套了
The whole place is disorganized.
West死了
West dead,
主管死了
the Chief dead,
计划书不见了
our papers stolen.
可是
And yet,
周一晚上我锁门的时候
when I closed this office on Monday evening
我们还和所有政府的办公室一样有效率
we were as efficient as any in the service.
周一办公室下班是几点?
What hour was the office closed on Monday?
五点
At 5:00.
是你锁的门?
Did you close it?
我一直是最后一个离开的
I'm always the last man out.
那晚上楼里有人巡视吗?
Is there a night watchman to the building?
是的
There is.
他同时也负责另外几个部门
He has other departments to look after as well.
他是个老兵
He's an old soldier.
非常可靠
A most trustworthy man.
那天晚上他什么都没看见
He didn't see anything that evening.
谢谢你
Thank you.
当你锁门的时候
When you closed the office
计划书在哪里?
where were the plans?
在保险柜里
In that safe.
我亲自放进去的
I put them there myself.
如果Cadogan West 要在下班后进入办公室
If Cadogan West was to enter the office after hours,
取走计划书
he would need three keys, would he not,
他必须有三把钥匙 对不对
before he could reach these papers.
是的 一把大门钥匙
Yes, a key to the outer door,
一把办公室门钥匙
a key to the office,
一把保险柜钥匙
and a key of the safe.
只有你和James Walter爵士
And only you and Sir James Walter
有这几把钥匙
had those keys.
是的
Yes, indeed.
James爵士把所有钥匙都串在一起
Sir James kept all three keys on one ring.
从不离身
They never left him.
当然了 你的钥匙也没离开过你
And, of course, your keys left your possession.
没有
Never.
先生 如果Cadogan West是罪犯
Sir, Cadogan West is the culprit.
那他必定是复制了钥匙
He must have had duplicates.
噢 就是他干的
Oh, he's the culprit all right.
想到West这样的人
It's dreadful to think that West of all people
会做出这种事 让人非常难过
should have done such a thing.
你确定他有罪?
You're sure of his guilt?
我没发现有别的可能
I see no other way.
他要结婚了
He was getting married,
他需要钱
he wanted the money.
是的 他就是你找的人
Oh yes, he's your man.
Johnson先生
Mr. Johnson,
如果有人想卖掉计划书
if someone desired to sell the plans
复制一份比拿走原件
surely it would be easier to make copies
不是要简单得多?
than to take the originals.
那需要一定的专业知识
It would need considerable technical knowledge.
可以让我看看吗
May I see these?
当然了
And, of course,
你和West还有James Walter爵士
you and West and Sir James Walter
都有这样的专业知识
have that knowledge.
应该是吧
That may be so,
但是别把我也扯进来 福尔摩斯先生
but don't try to drag me into this matter, Mr. Holmes.
计划书是在West身上找到的
The plans were found on West.
可奇怪的是
Well, it is certainly singular
明明复制文件更安全
that he should risk taking the originals
他却冒险拿走了原件
when he could have safely taken copies.
也许是时间问题
Perhaps it was a matter of time.
噢 是啊 时间
Oh, yes, time.
我知道 丢掉的3页计划书
Now, three plans are missing I understand,
-是非常重要的部分 -是这样的
-they are the vital ones. -That is so.
有人得到了这3页
Now, someone holding those three papers,
我是说 他们能不能
I mean, could they construct
造出布鲁斯-帕廷顿潜水艇呢?
the Bruce Partington Submarine?
向海军部报告时 我认为那很有可能
I told the Admiralty that I thought it was possible
但今天我不是很确定了
but today I'm not so sure.
这种极为重要的
These all important double-valves
双阀门自动调节孔的图样
with the automatic self-adjusting slots
是画在
are drawn only on this plan
已经找回的一张文件上的
which has been returned.
能不能请你
Would you be so kind
像周一晚上一样
as to close those window shutters
关上这些百叶窗
exactly as they were on Monday night.
百叶窗? 好的
Window shutters, certainly.
非常感谢
Thank you so much.
好的
Yes.
我想 我得出去走走了
I think I'll take a little stroll outside.
噢 请别担心
Oh, please don't trouble yourself.
我知道方位
I can find my own way.
稍等
Would you please wait.
福尔摩斯
Holmes.
华生
Watson.
看这里
Look at this.
花丛被人压过
The bushes have been broken.
看看我身后的窗户
Now look at the windows behind me.
窗户中间没有合上
The shutters don't meet in the center.
如你所说 没合上
As you say, don't meet.
有意思吧
Interesting, don't you think?
8点15分 伦敦桥 我能肯定
8:15, the London Bridge.
你确定他就是Cadogan West?
You definitely recognize him as Cadogan West?
噢 是的 肯定是
Oh, yes, definitely.
我和他很熟 先生
I knew him well, sir.
他是老相识了
He was an old acquaintance.
我们上次寒暄到现在
Hardly a week went by
还不到一周
that we didn't pass the time of day together.
很难接受吧?
It's hard to believe, isn't it?
是啊 我周日晚上还跟妻子说
Yeah,I was saying to the wife early on Sunday night,
不对 是周六
no, I'm a liar, it was Saturday.
我说 没有铁路比伦敦的铁路
I said there is no safer railway
更安全了
than the London Metropolitan.
看上去 West先生是在跟踪谁吗?
Did Mr. West seem to be following anyone?
我认为没有 福尔摩斯先生
Not that I saw, Mr. Holmes,
我什么都没看见
but then I don't see everything.
那天晚上雾非常大
There was really thick fog that night.
不过我可以看得出来
But one thing I will say
West先生和平时不一样
Mr. West wasn't his usual self.
他很紧张 很激动
He was nervous, excited.
这个人
I tell you this gentleman,
他的手抖得很厉害
his hand was shaking so bad.
还是我帮他拿的零钱
I had to open up his change.
嗯 我想这是不言而喻的
Well, I mean that speaks for itself.
我们的火车来了
请原谅
Our train.
Forgive us.
来吧 华生
Come Watson.
请进
Come in.
福尔摩斯先生?
Mr. Holmes.
福尔摩斯先生
在
Yes.
您出去的时候
Whilst you were away
政府有封信给您
a message came for you from the government.
政府来的?
From the government?
一个坐着官方马车的政府官员
A official gentlemen
他说在我把它交给你之前
in a special carriage.
He said I wasn't to let this out of my sight
绝不能让它离开我视线
until I placed it into your own hands.
Hudson太太
Mrs. Hudson,
你真是个忠实的人
you are a most faithful watchdog.
这是我哥哥Mycroft送来的
It's from my brother Mycroft.
他的笔迹就像喝醉的螃蟹一样
He writes like a drunken crab.
你最好看一看
You better read it.
医生对象形文字
Doctors are more used to hieroglyphics
比普通人更熟悉
than normal human beings.
噢 第一行就不认得
Oh, can't read the first bit.
什么小的发现
Something about small find,
大事件
very big affair.
啊 有了 "只有一个人值得怀疑"
Ah, here we are.
"Adolph Mayer"
Only men were considering
George街13号
Adolph Mayer,
真奇怪 那可不是他的风格
13 George Street
doubt it's him, it's not his style
噢 Hudson太太
Oh, Mrs. Hudson.
"Louis-"
Louis,
"Louis La Rothiere"
Louis La Rothiere
"Campden大厦"
of Campden Mansion,
"Notting Hill"
Notting Hill.
另一位老友
And that's another old friend.
Hudson太太 你挡着我了
Mrs. Hudson, your in the way.
-对不起先生 我只有一双手 -请离开吧
I'm sorry sir but I only have one pair of hands
Please disappear.
"Hugo Oberstein"
Ah, Hugo Oberstein,
"住在Kensington的Coffield花园13号"
13 Coffield Gardens, Kensington.
"据称 该人周一在城里"
Uh, known to be in town on Monday.
"现已离开"
Now reported to have left.
"内阁在急切盼望"
The Cabinet awaits your final report
"收到你的最终报告"
with the utmost anxiety.
"如果需要"
The whole force of the State is at your back
"整个英国的军队都归你调遣"
if you should need it.
"Mycroft"
Mycroft.
在这件事情上
All the queens' horses and all the queens' men
女王的兵马都无济于事
cannot avail us in this matter.
Coffield花园
Coffield Gardens.
好吧 好吧
Well, well.
发现什么了?
What have you found?
事情朝我们这边变化了
Things are turning a little in our direction.
现在我可以相信
Now I really believe
我们最终会胜利的
we're going to pull it off after all.
我要出去一趟
I'm going out.
什么时候回来?
When will you be back?
不确定 不过我保证
I have no idea but I promise I will
没有我最信任的伙伴兼传记作者在身边
do nothing serious without my trusty comrade
我不会冒险的
and biographer at my elbow.
他要我在Gloster路的一家餐馆
He wants me to meet him in a restaurant
和他见面
off of Gloster Road.
我希望你小心一点
I just hope you'll be careful
就这样
that's all.
你已经不年轻了
You're not as young as you were.
你知道福尔摩斯先生
You know what Mr. Holmes is like
一旦咬住就不松口
once he gets the bit between his teeth.
我知道
I do indeed.
晚安 Hudson太太
Goodnight Mrs. Hudson.
晚安 医生
Goodnight doctor.
谢谢
Thank you.
谢谢 先生
Thank you, sir.
请这边坐
Have you the tools.
吃过饭了吗?
Have you had something to eat?
吃过了
Yes, indeed.
那就来杯咖啡或者甜酒吧
Then have a coffee or a curacao.
Gardeni先生
Senor Gardeni,
来一杯咖啡加一杯甜酒 给我的朋友
a coffee and a curacao please, for my friend.
试试他们这的雪茄吧
Try one of the proprietor cigars.
是没有毒的
They're nothing like as poisonous
不像人们想象那样
as one would expect.
噢 谢谢
Oh, thank you.
那么
Now,
关于我们行动的计划
for our plan of action.
华生 你现在也应该清楚
It was evident to you Watson
尸体是被人
that the body was placed
放在了车顶上
on the roof of the carriage.
也许是从桥上掉下来的
Or dropped from a bridge.
不 那不可能 肯定是放上去的
No, that's impossible, placed.
车顶是弧形的 四周没有栏杆
The carriage roofs are rounded with no rails.
但是如何放在上面的呢
But how could he be placed there?
某些路段
In some areas
伦敦的地铁
the London underground
是没有隧道的
runs clear of tunnels
而且恰好经过某些房子后面
and past the backs of houses.
当我发现
When I found
一位重要的国际特务
that a leading international agent
就住在这样的房子里
lived in just such a house.
看到你对我突然草率的举动表示吃惊 真让我高兴
I was so pleased that you were a little astonished
Hugo Oberstein
at my sudden [unintelligible].
Coffield花园13号
Hugo Oberstein
13, Coffield Gardens, of course.
没错
Exactly.
更令我满意的是
I was able to satisfy myself that not only
不仅那里的后窗朝向铁路
而且地处Richmond线 和Wyndam线的交汇处
do the backstairs windows open over the line
but the bowing to the intersection
of the Richmond and Wyndam lines
主干线的交叉点
were the Circle Line.
靠近Gloster路车站
Near Gloster road Station.
日常来往的火车
The trains are frequently held motionless
恰好会在那个地方停留
at that very spot.
太精彩了 你解决了
That's splendid.
那栋房子已经人去楼空
You got it.
Oberstein显然已经离开这个国家
There house appears to be unoccupied.
处理他的战利品呢
Oberstein obviously has gone abroad
他没理由害怕搜捕
to dispose of his booty
has no reason to fear a warrant.
也根本不会想到
And to spot an amateur burglary
有人会潜入他的住宅
would never occur to him
但我们就要这么做
but that is precisely what we're about to do.
为什么
Why, for what purpose?
我们要找到他们联络的信件
We cannot tell what correspondence
不 我不喜欢这样 福尔摩斯
they may have.
No, I don't like it, Holmes.
你可以放哨
You can keep watch.
犯法的事情我来做
I'll do the criminal part.
现在不是计较细节的时候
This is no time to stick to trifles.
想想海军部 想想内阁
Think of the Admiralty, think of the cabinet.
想想那位我们不能直呼其名的高贵女士
Think of the exalted person
herself who [unintelligible].
我们必须这么做
We're bound to go.
我知道你最终不会退缩的
I knew you wouldn't shrink at the last.
棘手的问题
Serious proposition,
上锁了 也上了门闩
locked and bolted.
我们最好去地下室
We may do better down there
啊 好多了
Ah, this is better.
福尔摩斯
Holmes.
别碰
Don't touch this.
这是他们放尸体的地方
Look where they've rested the body.
血迹
Blood.
这里也有
Blood again.
你怎么看?
Well, what do you think of that?
杰作
Masterpiece.
前所未有的成就
You've never risen to a greater height.
不 我可不同意
No, I cannot agree with you.
从我想到尸体
The moment I conceived the idea of the body
是被放在车顶的那一刻起
on the roof of the train
剩下的都是显而易见的了
the rest was inevitable.
嗯 新的吸墨纸
Hmm, fresh blotting paper.
为了掩盖痕迹
He's covered his tracks.
福尔摩斯
Holmes.
没有有用的
Means nothing.
似乎烧过旧报纸
Seems to have been burning old newspapers.
-我说福尔摩斯 -嗯
I say Holmes
为什么一个明显
Yes.
又脏又乱的男人
Why would a man so obviously
要费心去烧旧报纸呢
untidy of his habits
take the trouble to burn old newspapers?
也许想生火
Probably trying to start a fire.
是啊  不对 没有木柴也没有炭
Yeah, but there's no, no wood or coal.
我看看
Let me see.
-哈 -是什么
Ha.
What is it?
干得好哇
Well done, well done.
我想我们找到要找的人了
Indeed, I think we have our man.
你来看看这两版 上的寻人广告栏
Would you look in the agony column
我们可以找到一个 自称Piero的人发的消息
of the two remaining copies of The Daily Telegraph.
I think you will find a message from someone
Piero Piero Piero
calling himself Piero.
啊 有了
Piero, Piero, Piero.
"请尽快回复 同意条件"
Ah, here we are.
"但务必要完整报告"
Hope to hear soon the terms agreed
-"联系人Piero" -下一份
but must have full report.
Matter pressing signed Piero.
没错 上帝啊
Yes, by Jove.
"周一晚九时后 门上敲两下"
Monday night after 9:00, two taps, only on sills,
"交货后即付硬币"
payment in hard cash when goods delivered,
和那条一样 署名是Piero
signed Piero just like the other one.
每份报纸上都有
Every paper has a message
这个自称Piero人发的消息
这是个假名
from someone calling himself Piero.
就像Oberstein这种恶棍会用的
It's an odd name
要是我们可以
for the villain like Oberstein to use.
在另一头抓住这个人就好了
If only we could get the man
华生 快来
at the other end.
我们没时间耽搁了
Watson, quickly,
带上报纸
we haven't a moment to loose.
Bring the papers.
我们要去哪?
Where we going?
报社 正好能赶上
The offices of the Daily Telegraph
精彩 真是精彩
Splendid job, splendid.
我经常说
I always said
如果你愿意
you'd the make best cat burglar in London
你会是伦敦最厉害的贼
if you put your mind to it.
警察可不能这么干 福尔摩斯先生
Can't do these things on the force, Mr. Holmes.
难怪你能比我们走得更远
No wonder you get results that are beyond us.
不过总有一天 你会走得太远
Some of these days you'll go too far
给你和你的朋友带来麻烦
and you and your friend
我们肩负着祖国的重托 华生
will find yourselves in trouble.
甘当国家的殉道者
England home and duty, Watson.
的寻人广告
Motto and the oath of our country.
The agony column of The Daily Telegraph.
你这是做什么用?
What use would you make of those?
你看过今天Piero 发的启事了吗?
Have you seen the advertisement
from Piero today?
"今晚 老时间 老地点"
Tonight, same hour, same place,
"敲两下 非常重要"
two taps, most vitally important,
"性命攸关 署名Piero"
your own safety at sake, signed Piero.
我保证 如果他行动了 我们就能抓住他
By George,
if he answers that we've got him.
醒醒
Wake up.
他来了
He's here.
你可以把我写成一个笨蛋 华生
You can write me down as an ass, Watson.
这可不是我能料到的家伙
This is not the bird I was expecting.
他是谁?
Who is he?
Valentine Walter上校
Colonel Valentine Walter,
James爵士的弟弟
Sir James' younger brother.
我要看看底牌了
I'm beginning to see how the cards fall now.
这是怎么回事?
What is this?
我是来找Oberstein先生的
I came here to visit Mr. Oberstein.
我认识你 当然了..
I know you, surely...
夏洛克 福尔摩斯
Sherlock Holmes.
一切都水落石出了 上校
Everything is known, Colonel.
一个英国绅士
How an English gentlemen
居然做出这等行为
could behave in such a manner
真让人费解
is beyond comprehension.
我们知道你和Oberstein的关系
We know of your relations
也发现了你们的联系方式
and correspondence with Oberstein.
你偷了你哥哥的钥匙
You stole your brothers' keys
复制了一套
and had them duplicated.
我们知道你周一晚上 去了海军办公室
We knew you went to Admiralty Office
被Cadogan West发现
on Monday night
作为一个正直的公民
and was seen by Cadogan West.
Being the good citizen that he was.
他在浓雾之中紧紧跟着你
He followed you closely in the fog
穿过了半个伦敦
halfway across London
直到你到了这所房子
until you reached this very house.
之后 Walter上校的叛国罪上面
It was then Colonel Walter that to treason
还要加上谋杀罪
you added the terrible crime of murder.
不是我
I did not.
我不是 我发誓 不是我干的
I did not before God.
那就告诉我们
I swear I did not.
在你们把他的尸体放上火车之前
Then tell us how Arthur Cadogan West
Arthur Cadogan West 是怎么死的?
met his end before you placed his body
如你所说 他一直跟着我
on the roof of the railway carriage?
He followed me as you described
到了这里的大门口
but until I was at the very door of this house
我才发现
I did not know it.
你拿着这些文件要做什么?
What are you gonna do with those papers?
他的头撞在了大理石地板上
He hit his head
几分钟以后就死了
on the marble floor.
He was dead in a matter of minutes.
是Oberstein的主意
It was Oberstein's idea
把不那么重要的文件 放在West的口袋里
to stuff the less important plans
然后把他扔到火车顶上
in West's pocket
and put him on the roof of the train.
是什么让你走上了叛国之路 上校?
What made you turn traitor, Colonel?
我有一大笔证券债务要偿还
A stock exchange debt had to be paid.
非常非常需要钱
I needed the money badly.
Oberstein出价5000磅
Oberstein offered me five thousand.
可以使我免于破产 声败名裂
It was to save myself from ruin and disgrace.
我哥哥以前和我讨论事情
My brother used to discuss matters with me
他实在不应该那么做
which he probably should not have done.
潜水艇计划
This submarine, for instance.
他怎么能想到
How could he ever guess
是他的亲弟弟背叛了他?
his own brother would betray him?
最糟糕的是
That was the worst of all.
他早怀疑我了 我知道的
He suspected me.
我能从他的眼神中看出来
I know he did.
I read it in his eyes.
West出事之后
And after this West business
他再也抬不起头来了
he never held up his head again.
嗯 你愿不愿意弥补你的过错
Can you not make reparation, hmmm,
减轻你的羞愧
to ease your conscious
甚至是你的惩罚?
and possibly your punishment?
我能怎么弥补?
What reparation can I make?
Oberstein带着文件去了哪里?
Where is Oberstein with the papers?
我不知道
I do not know.
他说写信到巴黎的Delu酒店 可以联系到他
He said that letters to the Hotel Delu in Paris
啊 那你就可以帮我们了
would reach him.
Ah, well then it is possible
for you to help us.
过来坐下
Come and sit down
我说你写
and write my dictation.
"亲爱的先生"
Dear sir,
"关于我们的交易"
in regard to our transaction
"你也许已经发现"
you have now observed
"尚缺一个重要细节"
that one essential detail is missing
"我这里已有图纸"
but I have a tracing
"可使其完整"
that will make it complete.
是真的吗 夏洛克?
Is that true, Sherlock?
千真万确
Quite true.
缺少什么重要的细节?
What essential detail is missing?
双阀门
The double-valves,
自动调节孔
the automatic self-adjusting slots.
我的天哪 你是怎么知道的?
Good heavens.
我已经是个潜水艇专家了
How on earth did you know that?
I've become quite a submarine expert
我亲爱的哥哥
brother of mine.
上校
Now Colonel,
你打算要价多少?
what would be your terms?
"我要额外增加500磅"
I must ask you for a further 500 pounds,
"只要英镑"
English notes please.
"我期待在..."
I should expect to meet you...
嗯 我们不能写这里
well, we can hardly say here
Oberstein会怀疑是陷阱的
or Oberstein will suspect a trap.
在Charring Cross酒店的大堂见面吧
The foyer of the
靠近火车站
Charring Cross Hotel.
Its proximity to the railway station
想必在国际特务中间
renders it extremely popular
很有名呢
amongst the international spy fraternity.
你听见了吗 上校?
Did you get that Colonel?
"下周六中午"
Noon, Saturday next.
如果这都不能引蛇出洞
I should be very surprised
我会非常吃惊的
if that does not flush our man out.
人来了
That's our man.
好啊 Bradstreet
Splendid Bradstreet.
不过我们的叛国者逃了
But our traitor has flown.
真是个小人
What a damn cheat of a fellow
再见了 先生们
Goodbye, gentlemen.
我会追他到天涯海角
I'm keeping him on a long lead.
天气真冷啊 (从"九月"到"四月"的寒冷季节里都有单词R 有"不到这时候不要吃牡蛎"的说法)
There's an R in the month
我知道Diogenes俱乐部
and the Diogenes Club
供应最棒的牡蛎
has the most excellent oysters.
我想请你们两位一起来品尝一下
I should like both you gentlemen to be my guests.
走吧 夏洛克
Come along, Sherlock.